Guide to the American Civil Liberties Union of North Carolina Records, 1960-2020; 1960-ongoing and undated RL.00012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Legal Program Series, 1968-2006 and undated, 260 boxes
  - Case Files Subseries, 128 boxes
    - 2000s Case Files, 1998-2005
      - Davidson Co. custody case: sexual orientation (Box 231)
      - Domestic violence/employment issues (Box 231)
      - Durham Co. inmates: close restraints (Box 231)
      - Durham Co. judicial building (Box 231)
      - East Bladen High School: transgender student (Box 231)
      - East Chapel Hill High School: lacrosse team led Bible study sessions (Box 231)
      - Email system to parents at charter school (Box 231)
      - Fayetteville peace rally: public park access (Box 231)
      - Forsyth Co. Schools: day of silence (Box 231)
      - Franklin County Board of Elections (Box 231)
      - Gideons: Columbus County (Box 231)
      - Gospel Choir: Chatham County (Box 231)
      - Macon County: Creationism (Box 231)
      - Christian ministry in the national parks (Box 231)
      - Closed investigation (Box 231)
      - Athens Drive High School: Baccalaureate (Box 231)
      - Birkhead/Duke University Police Department (Box 231)
      - Burke County Board of Elections (Box 231)
      - Buncombe County: religious headgear (Box 231)
      - Carteret Co. Schools (Box 232)
      - Ceremonial wine in Halfway House (Box 232)
      - Clay Co., Hayesville Court House: Ten Commandments (Box 232)
      - Harnett Co.: submission, 2 folders (Box 232)
      - Clayton Homes, interracial relationship fair housing issue, 7 folders (Box 232)
      - Right to Pardon, expungement, 7 folders (Box 232)
      - Church services in court (Box 232)
      - Cub scout recruitment (Box 232)
      - Lincoln Co. Representation (Box 232)
      - Military recruitment (Box 232)
      - Religion in Madison Co. schools, 2 folders (Box 232)
      - Closed without action, 20 folders (Box 233)
      - Voting Rights Act, Harnett County, 25 folders (Box 233)
      - Student's civil liberties, printed material, 2 folders (Box 234)
      - Memos (Box 234)
      - Reports (Box 234)
      - Correspondence (Box 234)
      - Out of school suspensions (Box 234)
      - Student's rights manual, 2 folders (Box 234)
      - Research:
        - Student press (Box 234)
        - The Ten Commandments (Box 234)
        - Dress codes, 2 folders (Box 234)
        - Day of silence / day of truth (Box 234)
        - Counterprotests (Box 234)
        - Right not to stop (Box 234)
      - Religious liberties, teachers (Box 234)
      - Solicitation of clients (Box 234)
      - Recording public meetings (Box 234)
      - Religious liberties, teaching about religion (Box 234)
      - Reproductive rights, students (Box 234)
      - Off campus student speech (Box 234)
      - ACLU, agreements and policies (Box 234)
      - Racial profiling (Box 234)
      - Public school disc.: anonymous internet issue (Box 234)
      - Prison and jail conditions (Box 234)
      - Religious Land Use and Institutionalized Persons Act of 2000 (RLIUPA) (Box 234)
      - ACLU sample policy guidelines, 4 folders (Box 235)
      - Supreme Court summaries, 1992-2003, 2 folders (Box 235)
      - Fourth Circuit cases, 2005, 6 folders (Box 235)
      - D.D.Y. (minor child): child abuse, neglect, 5 folders (Box 236)
      - Wrongful termination, 3 folders (Box 236)
      - Search warrant, 9 folders (Box 236)
      - Recording Industry Association of America (RIAA) v. UNC: internet file sharing, 2003-2004, folders 1-6 of 23 (Box 236)
      - RIAA v. USA, 2003-2004, folders 7-23 of 23 (Box 237)
      - Fifth amendment, involuntary confession, 4 folders (Box 237)
      - 11th amendment, immunity (Box 238)
      - Morrisville taxi ordinance, 12 folders (Box 238)
      - Race in murder trial, 11 folders (Box 238)
      - Signature requirements for new parties in election (Box 239)
      - Wiccan group denied access to Kill Devil Hills library, 2 folders (Box 239)
      - State Highway Patrol, 13 folders (Box 239)
      - Burden of proof to show waived Miranda rights knowingly and intelligently, folders 1-5 of 6 (Box 239)
      - Waived Miranda rights, folder 6 of 6 (Box 240)
      - FLOC organizers arrest file (Box 240)
      - Habitual felon law, 10 folders (Box 240)
      - Hunt High poster case: school censorship, 8 folders (Box 240)
      - CAN arrest in Brunswick County (Box 241)
      - Gaston County car search policy, Ballard, 4 folders (Box 241)
      - Green party certification petition case, 2 folders (Box 241)
      - Right to stop, 8 folders (Box 241)
      - Reproductive freedom project, Briefing packet to help you oppose so called partial-birth abortion bans, ACLU (Box 241)
      - Students' rights information, 8 folders (Box 242)
      - Rockingham County schools, 4 folders (Box 242)
      - Fourth Amendment, roadblock case, 19 folders (Box 243)
      - Clipping, schools, 1990 (Box 243)
      - Marijuana possession, illegal search and seizure, 9 folders (Box 243)
      - DNA testing as search, 10 folders (Box 244)
      - Miranda Rights, folders 1-10 of 13 (Box 244)
      - Miranda Rights, folders 11-13 of 13 (Box 245)
      - Court congestion, right to a speedy trial, 8 folders (Box 245)
      - ADA case, 11 folders (Box 245)
      - Due process, 4 folders (Box 246)
      - Suppression of drug evidence case, 3 folders (Box 246)
      - Indigent Defense Services, 10 folders (Box 246)
      - Due process, 4 folders (Box 246)
      - Discriminatory termination of employment, folders 1-5 of 6 (Box 246)
      - Discriminatory termination of employment, folders 6 of 6 (Box 247)
      - Constitutionality of sex offender registration statute, 6 folders (Box 247)
      - Sex discrimination, 4 folders (Box 247)
      - Medical malpractice rule, 8 folders (Box 247)
      - Fayetteville: religion in school (Box 247)
      - Edenton/Chowan dress code (Box 247)
      - Violation of confrontation clause (Box 247)
      - Violation of public meetings act (Box 248)
      - In God We Trust, Davidson County government center, 3 folders (Box 248)
      - Entrapment, 12 folders (Box 248)
      - Nash County school uniform policy, 5 folders (Box 248)
      - Tarboro protest case, 5 folders (Box 249)
      - Pervasive religious indoctrination in public schools, 6 folders (Box 249)
      - Nudity in plays (Box 249)
      - Catawba seal (Box 249)
      - Town of Cary, political sign ordinance (Box 249)
      - Alexander County, Ten Commandments in courthouse and commissioner resolution (Box 249)
      - Transylvania County, internet blocking at public libraries, 3 folders (Box 249)
      - Wilkes County: Ten Commandments, 7 folders (Box 250)
      - Establishment clause, 4 folders (Box 250)
      - Admissions discrimination case, folder 1 of 5 (Box 250)
      - Admissions discrimination case, folders 2-5 of 5 (Box 251)
      - Universal Life Church, Inc. (ULC) v. United States: ULC minister wants to perform marriage ceremonies (Box 251)
      - Southeast Raleigh High School unconstitutional graduation attire requirement (Box 251)
      - Sex offender, due process (Box 251)
      - Man with 67 IQ on death row, folders 1-3 of 5 (Box 251)
      - Man with 67 IQ on death row, folders 4-5 of 5 (Box 252)
      - Blue Cross Blue Shield (BCBS) v. Orange County: County civil rights ordinance, 9 folders (Box 252)
      - Fifty dollar indigent defense fee case, 6 folders (Box 253)
      - Public records act request, Work First North Carolina, welfare, 7 folders (Box 253)
      - Charlotte parade ordinance, 2 folders (Box 253)
      - Gaston County: Ten Commandments in County Commissioner's office (Box 253)
      - Homeless voter registration (Box 253)
      - Pregnant student: title IX (Box 254)
      - Skyland Fire Dept.: religious web site and fish symbol of department vehicles (Box 254)
      - Constitutionality of punitive damages cap, 2001, 4 folders (Box 254)
      - Campaign finance, 2000, folders 1-6 of 9 (Box 254)
      - Campaign finance, 2000, folders 7-9 of 9 (Box 255)
      - Raleigh nuisance party ordinance, 2003-2004, 5 folders (Box 255)
      - Beer label case, 7 folders (Box 255)
      - Constitutionality of state law against fortune telling, folders 1-3 of 8 (Box 255)
      - Constitutionality of state law against fortune telling, folders 4-8 of 8 (Box 256)
      - Fourth Amendment issue (Box 256)
      - Right to a speedy trial, 6 folders (Box 256)
      - Lesbian adoption, full faith and credit, 5 folders (Box 256)
      - Fifth Amendment issue, folders 1-6 of 16 (Box 256)
      - Fifth Amendment issue, folders 7-16 of 16 (Box 257)
      - Department of Social Services case, question over what constitutes sufficient cause for an investigation of neglect, 8 folders (Box 257)
      - Driving While Black cases (DWB), 12 folders (Box 258)
      - DWB, pleadings and briefs, 1-2 of 4 folders (Box 258)
      - DWB, pleadings and briefs, 3-4 of 4 folders (Box 259)
      - Affirmative Action (Box 259)
      - Accountant (Box 259)
      - ACLU publications list (Box 259)
      - Letters:
        - ACLU (Box 259)
        - General (Box 259)
        - Membership, 2 folders (Box 259)
      - Higher education act, financial aid and drug convictions (Box 259)
      - Our offer and Senator Edward's office response, 2004 (Box 259)
      - Confrontation clause (Box 259)
      - Correspondence with Robert Mostellor (prof. of law) (Box 259)
      - Research for amicus brief and memo (Box 259)
      - Seth Jaffe, 3 folders (Box 259)
      - Curfew (Box 260)
      - Memos/research (Box 260)
      - News clippings (Box 260)
      - Beneficient provision for the poor (Box 260)
      - Welfare County plans, Work First, 6 folders (Box 260)
      - Abortion research, 3 folders (Box 261)
      - Curfews research, 6 folders (Box 261)
      - Ten Commandments, 2 folders (Box 262)
      - Begging, 7 folders (Box 262)
      - SB 452, local adult entertainment (Box 262)
      - SB 228, child abuse reporting (Box 262)
      - Fourth and Fourteenth Amendments, 4 folders (Box 263)
      - Drug test, Fourth Amendment, 10 folders (Box 263)
      - Chapel Hill, aggressive panhandling and Raleigh, sleeping in parks, 2 folders (Box 263)
      - Chapter boards (Box 264)
      - Cross on town seal, 2 folders (Box 264)
      - Grants and solicitations (Box 264)
      - Hemlock society (Box 264)
      - Frank Porter Graham Awards Dinner (Box 264)
      - Redistricting [maps removed to Oversize Material] (Box 264)
      - Buncombe school board policy unconstitutional, 2002, 8 folders (Box 264)
      - Racial profiling, 1-3 of 7 folders (Box 264)
      - Racial profiling, 4-7 of 7 folders (Box 265)
      - Governmental immunity, 5 folders (Box 265)
      - Northwestern Regional Library: internet filter policy (Box 265)
      - Protest issue in city of Brevard (Box 265)
      - Ban of Confederate flag on clothes in school (Box 265)
      - Macon County Nativity scene, 2001-2003, 6 folders (Box 265)
      - Bible distribution in NC schools, 4 folders (Box 266)
      - Sexual discrimination, 3 folders (Box 266)
      - Board Members, 2 folders (Box 266)
      - Bill of Rights proclamation (Box 266)
      - Governor's declarations (Box 266)
      - DMV regulations: proof of identity issue, 3 folders (Box 266)
      - Free speech activities in Pack square, 2003 (Box 266)
      - Catawba County seal, folder 1 of 3 (Box 266)
      - Catawba County seal, folders 2-3 of 3 (Box 267)
      - NC sodomy law (Box 267)
      - Cary political sign ordinance, 5 folders (Box 267)
      - NC session law, 2004-125: campaign finance, 4 folders (Box 267)
      - Seth's Judicial Bypass folder, 1-3 of 7 folders (Box 267)
      - Seth's Judicial Bypass folder, 4-7 of 7 folders (Box 268)
      - Buncombe, Haywood, and Rowan County Entanglement: religion in schools, 5 folders (Box 268)
      - Dog-limit ordinances (Box 268)
      - Dress code/uniform complaints (Box 268)
      - DWB racial profiling complaints (Box 268)
      - DWB statistics gathering Law (Box 268)
      - Experts - police and otherwise (Box 268)
      - Fayetteville school uniforms (monitor) (Box 268)
      - Columbine High School, 2 folders (Box 269)
      - Juvenile death penalty research (Box 269)
      - Hearsay in Domestic Court (Box 269)
      - Catalyst fees (Box 269)
      - Legislative prayer decision, Fourth Circuit (Box 269)
      - LGBT brochure 13 Things to Know, 4 folders (Box 269)
      - Grants to State Residents Enrolled in Post-Secondary Religious Institutions, 2001 (Box 270)
      - Durham Public School faculty meeting prayer, 2002 (Box 270)
      - UNC Chapel Hill summer reading requirement (Box 270)
      - Warsaw Parade Ordinance, 2002 (Box 270)
      - Wake County drug testing kits for schools, 2002 (Box 270)
      - Wilkes County School Board, Mulberry Elementary: prayer in schools (Box 270)
      - Jacksonville police, 2003: driving while black (Box 270)
      - United Life Church Minister refused admission to hospital to minister patients, 2002 (Box 270)
      - Wilmington City Council prayer, 2002 (Box 270)
      - Driving while black, 2002 (Box 270)
      - Teaching tolerance for homosexuals in NC, 2001 (Box 270)
      - Segregated domestic violence court in Charlotte, 2000 (Box 270)
      - Wiccan suspended from East Burke High School because of pink hair, 2001 (Box 270)
      - Rockingham County Ten Commandments, 2002 (Box 270)
      - Vivid television case, 2001 (Box 270)
      - Raleigh Anti-Job Solicitation Ordinance, 2002 (Box 270)
      - Student expelled for praying the rosary at a Baptist school, 2002 (Box 270)
      - Potential Intern Projects (Box 271)
      - Blakely issue, 2004, 2 folders (Box 271)
      - Alamance County mistreatment of Hispanics, 2003 (Box 271)
      - Complaint of unreasonable demands by Mint Hill, NC officials to allow a religious protest, 2004 (Box 271)
      - Complaint that public school has notice board with word "WOP" on it (Box 271)
      - Catawba County Seal, 2004 (Box 271)
      - Muslim headgear and driver's license ID photo, 2003 (Box 271)
      - School in church, 2003 (Box 271)
      - Greensboro school banning political buttons, 2004 (Box 271)
      - Rape Shield Law and Blakely Case, 2004 (Box 271)
      - Juvenile Justice PRA request information (Box 271)
      - Prayer at Durham Housing Authority Meeting, 2004 (Box 271)
      - Harnett Central High School: student suspended for wearing hair in dreadlocks, 2003 (Box 271)
      - Teacher passing out bible and leading prayer, 2003r (Box 271)
      - Off-campus internet site, 2003 (Box 271)
      - Libel and student newspaper, 2004 (Box 271)
      - Complaint about voting districts in Shelby, NC, 2004 (Box 271)
      - Onslow County internet use policy, 2003 (Box 271)
      - Claims son suspended from school for contents of "journal," 2003 (Box 271)
      - Large crosses erected in yards/rights of way in Polk County, 2003 (Box 271)
      - North Carolina School for Science and Math refuses to lend out public documents (Box 271)
      - Session Law 2003-398: Private Dog Dry Search Law (Box 271)
      - Religious policy in Caldwell County schools, 2004 (Box 271)
      - UNC Christian fraternity issue (Box 271)
      - School in a church, 2003 (Box 271)
      - American Security Ins. et al., 5 folders (Box 271)
      - Amicus Club and CLE Files, 4 folders (Box 272)
      - American flag case, 2001 (Box 272)
      - Topless at beach (Box 272)
      - Creedmar Church Tax exemption issue (Box 272)
      - Union County, 1999 (Box 272)
      - Prayers in Harnett County Schools (Box 272)
      - SEANC in Board of Elections (Box 272)
      - Traffic ticket quotas, 2001 (Box 272)
      - Pastoral summit, UNC-W (Box 272)
      - Checkpoint turnaround case (Box 272)
      - Wake County School: character education pamphlet, 2001 (Box 272)
      - Boat search (Box 272)
      - Boone Single family dwelling ordinance, 2001 (Box 272)
      - Enloe High School student suspended for off-campus website (Box 272)
      - Lincoln County School "Oh my God" case (Box 272)
      - Dr. convicted of marijuana use and only referred to religiously affiliated rehab, 2001 (Box 272)
      - Kindergarten class religious content (Box 272)
      - Bible distribution in public school (Box 272)
      - Appalachian State alcohol search policy, 2001 (Box 272)
      - Driving while black, 2001 (Box 272)
      - Jehovah's Witness practicing religion in prison (Box 272)
      - NC DENR change meeting time, protest (Box 272)
      - Student website case (Box 272)
      - Claims unlawfully arrested for failing "to obtain a permit allowing a visual recording or other audio or visual production work on the property of a state..." - Asheville, documentary on Thomas Wolfe (Box 272)
      - State training schools (Box 272)
      - ADA and UNCG, 2001 (Box 272)
      - Christmas songs in public school (Box 272)
      - Prayer prior to baseball game, East Chapel Hill (Box 272)
      - Social security number demanded by police during stop (Box 272)
      - Asheville high school confiscates book of spells (Box 272)
      - Material support provision to terrorist group, 2002 (Box 272)
      - Religious songs in a Buncombe County middle school (Box 273)
      - Homeless on State Capitol grounds, 2 folders (Box 273)
      - Raleigh panhandling ordinance (Box 273)
      - Mecklenberg County Bar: Establishment Clause (Box 273)
      - Ethnic profiling at Charlotte Airport, 3 folders (Box 273)
      - New Bern: Ten Commandments (Box 273)
      - Summer intern resumes (Box 273)
      - LGBT and AIDS project update, 2001-2002 (Box 274)
      - LGBT report to National, 2003-2004 (Box 274)
      - Liu, Chang (Box 274)
      - Liberty Project (Box 274)
      - Michelle Stuff (Box 274)
      - NC Court of Appeals interesting decisions (Box 274)
      - ACLU events and activities calendars, 2 folders (Box 274)
      - Various ACLU-NC Court decisions, 1997-2000 (Box 274)
      - ACLU press releases and other info (Box 274)
      - Bishop, Bridget (Box 274)
      - Cooperating attorneys, 2000-2003 (Box 274)
      - County and City attorney list (Box 274)
      - Carole DeSouza file (Box 274)
      - Eastern District NC Federal Court Orientation (Box 274)
      - Getting Organized Seminar Materials (Box 274)
      - Ghoorah, Andrea (Box 274)
      - Glover, Jordan (Box 274)
      - July 2000 update: God and Country in the Public Schools (Box 274)
      - Henry, James (Box 274)
      - Horowitz, Jon (Box 274)
      - Summer internships, 4 folders (Box 274)
      - Lam, Hoang (Box 274)
      - Legal Committee confidentiality memo (Box 274)
      - Asheville racial profiling, 2003 (Box 275)
      - See You At The Pole, Canton NC Elementary School, 2000-2001 (Box 275)
      - Elementary school bible distribution, 2002 (Box 275)
      - Prisoner claims denied right to vote in jail (Box 275)
      - Ex-DOC employee says denied right to marry prisoner, 2001 (Box 275)
      - Harassment (Box 275)
      - Brunswick County School, Fourth Amendment, 2002 (Box 275)
      - Fourth Amendment, 2001 (Box 275)
      - Henderson County Public Demonstration Ordinance, 2001 (Box 275)
      - Correspondence course ban for death row inmates, 2001 (Box 275)
      - Fayetteville Fire Department, 1999: religious content in newsletter (Box 275)
      - Atheist at Fort Bragg Abused (Box 275)
      - Cary Police Social Security Number, 2001 (Box 275)
      - First Amendment, 2001 (Box 275)
      - Native American marriage ceremony not recognized by the state, 1999 (Box 275)
      - Transylvania Public Library internet filters, 2002 (Box 275)
      - Peer review privilege in 1981 Amicus, 2000 (Box 275)
      - Alexander County Redistricting Plan, 2000 (Box 275)
      - Whiteville cruising ordinance, 2000 (Box 275)
      - Social Security numbers and government agency requests, 2000 (Box 275)
      - NC Constitution and Private Prisons, 2 folders (Box 276)
      - Immunization waiver at NC School for the Arts (Box 276)
      - Racial profiling at RDU (Box 276)
      - Intern, letters of recommendation (Box 276)
      - Intern, letters of recommendation (Box 276)
      - Externships, 2 folders (Box 276)
      - Dan Pollitt Award - 2004 applicants (Box 276)
      - Samples - Motion for leave to file amicus in state appellate courts (Box 276)
      - UHC Information - Health Insurance, 1998 (Box 276)
      - Wake County Court Orientation, 2000 (Box 276)
      - North Carolina Coalition for Adoption Reform (Box 276)
      - Religious police enforcing criminal law (Box 276)
      - Public school teachers supervising prayer, 2002 (Box 276)
      - Sixth Amendment and work product issues, 2003 (Box 276)
      - Raleigh police and social security numbers, 2003 (Box 276)
      - Franklin County Commissioner: prayer at meetings, 2003 (Box 276)
      - Indigent Defense, Appointment of Counsel, 2003 (Box 276)
      - FIRE: Shaw University, academic freedom, 2003 (Box 276)
      - Richmond County School Uniform Policy, 2003 (Box 276)
      - Drug dog sniff at road block, 2004 (Box 276)
      - Strip search case, 2003, 3 folders (Box 277)
      - Sixth Amendment, 2003, 15 folders (Box 277)
      - Whistleblower fired from Pamlico company, 2004 (Box 277)
      - New Hanover County: Ten Commandments in school, 2003 (Box 277)
      - Clemency letter and action alert, 2004 (Box 277)
      - Asheville police searches of dorm rooms, 2003 (Box 277)
      - ASU ban on religious candles, 2003 (Box 277)
      - North Carolina Bar Association program, Negotiating the Ethical Minefield (Box 277)
      - Look Out File, 3 folders (Box 278)
      - Indigent defense issue (Box 278)
      - Rocky Mount Charter School regulations regarding student hair (Box 278)
      - Lesbian visiting prison (Box 278)
      - Creedmore Public Relations Act violations (Box 278)
      - Removal of Klan rally sign (Box 278)
      - Confederate flag and mail delivery (Box 278)
      - Non-English written materials denied to prisoners (Box 278)
      - Havelock school uniform policy (Box 278)
      - Claims the guards in prison won't let his male visitor kiss him hello (Box 278)
      - Censorship of gay-themed art and the hanging of the Ten Commandments in public schools (Box 278)
      - Bibles passed out at Craven County Elementary (Box 278)
      - Clinton curfew ordinance (Box 278)
      - Blue Cross Blue Shield (BCBS) privacy complaint (Box 278)
      - Right to assembly in Asheville (Box 278)
      - Random search at Hoke County High School (Box 278)
      - Constitutionality of private prisons (Box 278)
      - North Carolina School of Science and Math internet restrictions (Box 278)
      - Complaint that the SOAR rehabilitation program in prisons results in violations of the Fifth Amendment (Box 278)
      - Sheriff fired an employee for not participating in his reelection campaign (Box 278)
      - Driving while black, 2 folders (Box 278)
      - Disjunctive jury, 2002, 4 folders (Box 279)
      - Scheduled execution of a mentally disabled person, 2 folders (Box 279)
      - Vagueness of statute, meth labs prosecuted as containing weapons of mass destruction, 2003-2004, 2 folders (Box 279)
      - Flawed indictment for first degree sexual offense, 2004, 3 folders (Box 279)
      - Sexual harassment and discrimination in Southern Pines police department, 2006 (Box 279)
      - Cary public finance ordinance (Box 279)
      - Angels in America, art censorship materials (Box 279)
      - Attorney fee case (Box 279)
      - Know your rights, student manual (Box 279)
      - Title IX (Box 279)
      - Your rights when stopped by police, card update (Box 279)
      - Voter registration (Box 279)
      - NC Department of Health and Human Services, listing of childcare centers (Box 279)
      - School Finance Group (Box 279)